<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peoples eccho to the Parliaments declarations, concerning a personall treaty with the King. Containing a collection of some few passages out of severall declarations and expresses of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament at Westminster, concerning a personall treaty with the King. Together with a humble enforcement of the equity and justice of the said expresses; humbly presented, not only to the review of the Honourable Parliament: but also to the serious consideration of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of London in Common-Councell assembled.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90447</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E459_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205103</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864541</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864541</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116771</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90447)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116771)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E459[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peoples eccho to the Parliaments declarations, concerning a personall treaty with the King. Containing a collection of some few passages out of severall declarations and expresses of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament at Westminster, concerning a personall treaty with the King. Together with a humble enforcement of the equity and justice of the said expresses; humbly presented, not only to the review of the Honourable Parliament: but also to the serious consideration of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of London in Common-Councell assembled.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116771:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Peoples ECCHO To the Parliaments DECLARATIONS, Concerning a Perſonall Treaty with the <hi>KING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing a Collection of ſome few paſſages out of ſeverall Declarations and Expreſſes of the <hi>LORDS</hi> and <hi>COMMONS</hi> aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> concerning a Perſonall Treaty with the <hi>KING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with an humble enforcement of the equity and juſtice of the ſaid Expreſſes; Humbly preſented, not only to the review of the Honourable Parliament: but alſo to the ſerious conſideration of the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons of <hi>LONDON</hi> in Common-Councell Aſſembled.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 59.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Judgement is farre from us, neither doth Juſtice overtake us. We wait for light, but behold obſcurity; for brightneſſe, but we walke in darkeneſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116771:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116771:2"/>
            <head>The Peoples Eccho to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Declarations concerning a Perſonall Treaty with the <hi>KING.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="documents">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Declaration of the Lords and Commons of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1647. in anſwer to the papers of the <hi>Scotch Commiſſioners,</hi> page 20.</note> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE aske what reaſon have we to expect better ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the way of a Treaty, then formerly wee had therein at <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> or in a Perſonall Treaty at <hi>Oxford,</hi>unleſſe we be reſolved before hand to treat away all that we have fought for, and to be treated out of all that wee could not be fought out of; or at leaſt what can we expect of a Treaty, but that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of ſatisfying all Intereſts, one Intereſt ſhall be ſet up againſt another to divide us: And that thereby having laid no foundation of ſafety before-hand, the King might ſet up His Intereſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them all.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> If wee cannot have Peace but upon theſe termes, <hi>viz.</hi> The will of the King, and the advantage of the Crowne in the Kings eſteeme. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon theſe termes we needed not to have any Warre, which had been much the more Chriſtian reſolution, and would have ſaved the effuſion of much blood; whereof if we proceed upon ſuch principles as thoſe, wee muſt needs draw the whole guilt upon our owne ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Decl. of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1647. pag. 24.</note> If the way of reaſon and perſwaſion be the only equall, faire,and juſt way to obtaine a well grounded Peace, &amp;c. we have gone in a very foule way hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, which ſhould have been taken into conſideration, before we had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged our ſelves and the Kingdome in ſo much coſt and blood, which was not only ſpent unneceſſarily, but alſo very unlawfully, if wee muſt goe no way but that of perſwaſion, &amp;c. who doth not ſee that theſe Principles doe not only BRING <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PON <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S ALL THE BLOOD THAT HATH BEEN SHED IN THIS WAR, but alſo plucketh up the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any hope of ever ſetling a Peace with the King, which ſhall be both juſt and ſure, ſeeing we cannot have it juſtly but upon his termes; which no man
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116771:3"/>that hath his eyes in his head can believe, that they will be other then ſuch as tend to the apparent deſtruction of the perſons which have engaged, and the loſſe of the ends for which both Kingdomes have engaged in this war.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Decl. of the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1647. pag. 25.</note> The bringing of the King to <hi>London</hi> for a Perſonall Treaty with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament before the maine points in difference between them be ſetled &amp; aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is to no other purpoſe, but to encreaſe that fond humour of confidence in miſled and deceived people, which prevaileth in them too much already before they have aſſurance; which they and their poſterity may after rue and repent, when it is too late to help it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Decl. of the 4. of <hi>March,</hi> 1647. pag. 21.</note> The Scotch Commiſſioners miſtake their aime, if they thinke the Kings preſence with the Parliament neceſſarily implieth his preſence at <hi>London,</hi> which <hi>HE</hi> and <hi>THEY</hi>ſo much deſire; <hi>THAT HE MIGHT HAVE OPPORTUNITY TO CAJOLE THE CITIZENS,</hi> &amp;c. His re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to his Parliament with the ſame affections and intentions; that is, to deſtroy and undermine his Parliament, and to renew the warre againſt them is as great a reaſon for his abſence from it, as his abſence formerly from it in order to deſtroy it, and to begin a warre againſt them was then a reaſon for his preſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Decl. of the 4. of <hi>March,</hi> 1647. pag. 86.</note> How <hi>BASE</hi> and <hi>DISHONOURABLE</hi> a thing would it have been for the houſes of Parliament being in that condition they are, to have treated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gallowes, to have treated as Traytors, their Cauſe being not juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor the Declarations againſt them as Rebels recalled: And how <hi>FOO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LISH</hi> a thing would it have been, being poſſeſſed of the ſword according to their right, not to ſecure it even from his owne claime to the contrary, to themſelves and poſterity before they treated of any thing, to the end that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they nor their Poſterity might be put to play another bloody game for the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners anſwer to his Majeſties Letters of the 26. &amp; 29. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1645.</note> Concerning the Perſonall Treaty deſired by your Majeſtie, there having beene ſo much innocent blood of your good Subjects ſhed in this warre <hi>BY YOUR MAJESTIES COMMANDS AND COMMISSIONS.</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Rebels brought over into both Kingdomes, and endeavours to bring over more into both of them; as alſo forces from Forreigne parts; Your Majeſtie being in Armes in theſe parts, the Prince in the head of an Armie in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> divers Townes made Garriſons, and kept in hoſtility by your Majeſtie againſt the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> There being alſo forces in <hi>Scotland</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Parliament and Kingdome <hi>BY YOUR MAJESTIES COMMISSION.</hi> The warre in <hi>Ireland FOMENTED AND PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LONGED BY YOUR MAJESTIE,</hi> whereby the three Kingdomes are brought neer to utter ruine and deſtruction; VVe conetive that untill ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116771:3"/>and ſecurity be firſt given to both your Kingdomes; Your Majeſties comming hither cannot be convenient, nor by us aſſented unto.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer of the Lords &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to His Majeſties meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the 25. of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642.</note> The Lords &amp; Commons in Parl. aſſembled, having received your Majeſties Meſſage of the <hi>25.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> doe with much griefe reſent the dangerous &amp; diſtracted ſtate of this Kingdom, which we have by all means endeavored to prevent, both by our ſeverall Advices and Petitions to your Majeſtie, which have been not only without ſucceſs: but there hath followed that which no ill Councell in former times hath produced, or <hi>ANY AGE HATH</hi> ſeen, namely thoſe ſeverall Proclamations and Declarations againſt both the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament, whereby their actions are declared treaſonable, and their perſons Traytors, and thereupon Your Majeſtie hath ſet up your Standard againſt them; whereby <hi>YOU HAVE PUT THE TWO HOUSES OF PARLIAMENT, AND IN THEM THIS WHOLE KINGDOME OUT OF YOUR PROTECTION:</hi> So that <hi>UNTILL</hi> your Majeſtie ſhall recall thoſe Proclamations aad Declarations, whereby the Earle of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex</hi> and both Houſes of Parliament, and their Adherents and Aſſiſtants, &amp; ſuch as have obeyed and executed their Commands and Directions, according to their duty, are declared Traytors, or otherwiſe Delinquents: And untill the Standard ſet up in purſuance of the ſaid Proclamations be taken downe, <hi>YOUR MAJESTIE HATH PUT US INTO SUCH A CONDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION;</hi> that whilſt we ſo remaine, we cannot by the fundamentall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, the publique truſt repoſed in us, or with the generall good and ſafety of this Kingdome, give your Majeſtie any other anſwer to this Meſſage—<hi>which was a denyall of a Treaty according to his Majeſties Meſſage untill as afo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſaid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Declaration o the 11. of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1647.</note> Reſolved upon the Queſtion by the Lords and Commons in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament aſſembled: <hi>That they doe declare that they will make no further addreſſes or applications to the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reſolved upon the Queſtion by the Lords and Commons: <hi>That no application or addreſſes be made to the King by any perſon whatſoever, without the leave of both Houſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reſolved upon the Queſtion by the Lords and Commons: <hi>That the perſon or perſons that ſhall make breach of this Order, ſhall incurre the penalties of HIGH TREASON.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reſolved upon the Queſtion by the Lords and Common: <hi>That they doe declare that they will receive no more any Meſſage from the King: and doe enjoyne that no perſon whatſoever doe preſume to receive or bring any Meſſage from the King to both or either of the Houſes of Parliament, or to any other Perſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="response">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116771:4"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccho.</hi>
                  </note> No more addreſſes or applications to be made to the King, no meſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to be brought from the King to both, or either of the Houſes of Parliament, or to any other Perſons? What meanes then the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bleating of the common people of a Perſonall Treaty with the King? Is it the uncertaine voyce of unſetled multitudes, or the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Vote of our preſent Parliament? If true as 'tis reported; how do our Councels ring changes? whoſe hearing ears we humbly crave to hearken to the <hi>ECCHO</hi> of their own language. Honoured Sirs, <hi>we aske what reaſon have you to expect better ſatisfaction in the way of a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then formerly you had therein at</hi> Uxbridge, <hi>or in a Perſonall treaty at</hi> Oxford. Can it enter into our hearts that THIS, EVEN THIS PARLIAMENT, whoſe Declarations, Proteſtations, Votes, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Ordinances, Vowes, Covenants, Promiſes, have fil'd the eares of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and the Chriſtian-world with words of gallantry, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, juſt liberty and freedome in the behalf of them that have betruſted them. THIS PARLIAMENT, whoſe ſeverall Expreſſes, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent promiſes to make us a happy &amp; free Nation, raiſed up the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and be-ſpirited the Kingdome, to ſtand by them in their hopefull endeavours to this end? THIS PARLIAMENT, in whoſe juſt Warre againſt an unjuſt enemy, ſo many Widows and Fatherleſſe have been made, ſo many families undone, ſo many houſes, Villages and Towns ſack'd and burnt, ſo many Hoſpitals fill'd with lame and maimed Souldiers; ſuch leadings into captivity, priſons and dungeons; ſuch ſhedding of teares, wringing of hands, ſorrowes, miſeries, and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of many kinds have been endured, and that after all THIS, THIS, EVEN THIS PARLIAMENT <hi>ſhould be reſolved to treate away all that they have ſought for, and to be treated out of what they could not be fought out of?</hi> We beſeech you ſatisfie our judgment ſo lately inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by your owne Declarations; <hi>What can you NOW expect of a treaty</hi> (eſpecially as things ſtand) <hi>but that under pretence of ſatisfying all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, one Intereſt ſhall be ſet up againſt another, to divide us: and that thereby having laid no foundation of ſafety before-hand, the King might ſet up his Intereſt above them all.</hi> They are your owne words, publiſhed on put poſe (as we conceive) for our information: Be not offended if we tell you, your hands have found out their enterprize; for your words have taken ſuch hold upon our hearts, that we cannot eaſily let them goe. We beſeech you <hi>what foundation of ſafety is laid?</hi> Is there any thing yet concluded between his Majeſtie and Parliament ſecuring the peace and ſaſety of the Kingdome as prævious to a Treaty? If none, <hi>ſhall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116771:4"/>you not have the way and termes of your peace cut out unto you?</hi> And what can that be but the laying a foundation of utter ſlavery and vaſſalage to this poore Nation? <hi>If you cannot have peace but upon ſuch termes,</hi> viz. <hi>the will of the King</hi> (as doubtleſſe you cannot if you muſt treat as Traytors, and the Kings printed Expreſſes ſo branding you, unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called) beare with the Eccho of your owne language. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon THESE termes you needed not have any Warres, which had been much the more Chriſtian reſolution, and would have ſaved the effuſion of much blood; whereof if we proceed upon ſuch principles as theſe,</hi> WEE MUST NEEDS DRAW THE WHOLE GUILT UPON OUR SELVES. The weight of your lines doe depreſs our ſpirits: and certain it is that they are the words of trueth and ſoberneſſe: And let that day be darkneſſe wherein, even this Parliament, <hi>ſhall draw the whole guilt of the blood</hi> (ſhed in theſe Warres) <hi>upon themſelves.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 3.3, 4.</note> Let not God regard that day, neither let the light ſhine upon it. Let darkneſſe and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death ſtaine it; let a cloud dwell upon it, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 10.16, 17.</note> let the blackneſſe of the day terrifie it. How will theſe lines of yours be (as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith) Gods witneſſes againſt you, and make him increaſe his indignation upon you; changes and warre will be upon you, and hunt you even at a fierce Lyon. Shall <hi>Englands</hi> Parliament, that Parliament of Parliaments, that eight yeares Parliament; which profeſt more of God, Reformation, Religion, then all Parliaments before them, with whom God did more viſibly appeare; for whoſe defence, ſafety, and protection, many a time did the Lord breake the heavens, and come downe, making mountaines plaines before them: That Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-making Parliament, that Sermon hearing Parliament, that have charged the blood of the late Warres upon their adverſe party, <hi>draw the whole guilt thereof upon themſelves,</hi> even by their owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? Can you ſuppoſe the way of reaſons and perſwaſions by a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the only faire and juſt way to a well-grounded Peace? Surely then your ſelves being Judges, <hi>you have gone in a very foule way hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, which ſhould have beene taken into conſideration before you had engaged your ſelves and Kingdome in ſo much coſt and blood</hi> (as your owne words are) <hi>which was not only ſpent unneceſſarily, but very unlawfully.</hi> And you further adde, <hi>who doth not ſee that theſe principles doe not only bring upon us all the blood that hath beene ſhedde in this Warre, but alſo plucketh up the foundation of any hope of ever ſetling a Peace with the King, that ſhall bee both juſt and ſure, ſeeing wee cannot have it juſtly but upon his</hi> (viz the Kings) <hi>termes, which no man that hath his eyes in his head,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116771:5"/>can beleeve that they will be other then ſuch as tend to the apparent deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the perſons which have engaged, and loſſe of the ends for which both Kingdomes have engaged in this warre.</hi> Can you beare your owne words, and ſtand in the day of ſuch a viſitation? Will you take ſuch a courſe and way after eight yeares ſtriving and ſtruggling in fire and blood, to ſettle the Kingdome, <hi>which ſhall pluck up the foundation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hope of ever ſetling a peace with the King which ſhall be both juſt and ſure?</hi> Hath not God given you ſuch wonderfull advantages by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing your enemies under your feet, to ſettle not onely a <hi>juſt,</hi> but a <hi>ſure</hi> peace, and will you neglect the day of ſuch grace? Will you now at laſt take ſuch a way to ſettle peace, viz. <hi>by having it upon the Kings tearms, which no man that hath his eye in his head, can beleeve that they will be other then ſuch as tend to the apparent deſtruction of the perſons which have engaged, and loſſe of the ends for which both Kingdomes have engaged in this warre?</hi> Will not the blood that hath been already ſhed in theſe warres, bring in judgement enough, and wrath enough, but that thoſe of the well-affected party that doe yet remain alive, <hi>muſt likewiſe apparently be deſtroyed</hi> for adhering unto you? Have we ſpent our eſtates, our trades, our limbs, our lives for you, and muſt <hi>appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent deſtruction</hi> be our reward? Is this your requitall of us? Is this that juſt freedome which you promiſed? Well, if it muſt be ſo, <hi>Fiat voluntas Domini.</hi> The expence of our former treaſure and blood is ſo far from being matter of repentance unto us, that we reſolve through the ſtrength of our God, to chuſe rather to let this <hi>apparent deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> triumph over us, and even hurry us into the pit of ſilence, reſt &amp; peace, in confident expectation of a moſt advantagious reſurrection, then to turn head upon our juſt principles, and ſtrike hands with a revolting and apoſtatizing generation; but muſt not onely the <hi>PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SONS that have engaged,</hi> but <hi>the ENDS alſo for which they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged,</hi> in joyning with you, be <hi>apparently deſtroyed?</hi> Is not the blood of men ſufficient to provoke God, and bring wrath, but muſt the life even of truth it ſelfe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Kingdomes cauſe and <hi>ends</hi> of our <hi>engagement,</hi> aſſiſt herein?</p>
               <p>We are not abſolutely againſt a treaty, your wiſdoms judging it meet as the caſe ſtands; in whom we acquieſce: but that you ſhould reſolve to treat before thoſe things neceſſarily prævious to a treaty be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we would gladly ſee a reaſon for it, that we might be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it: For though we hold our ſelves bound in conſcience to ſatisfie our ſelves with vour iudgment in things diſoutable and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſall;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116771:5"/>troverſall; yet in things obvious and plain, we expect to have better' ſatisfaction then the vote of the Houſes, eſpecially themſelves having ſo ſully informed us about the abſolute neceſſity of thoſe things.</p>
               <p>We are not ignorant, but that you may lawfully vote, and revoke, and re vote again, order, un order, and re order, ordaine, repeale, and re ordaine the ſame things over &amp; over, all conducing in your beſt apprehenſions to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſafety; yea that Religion, reaſon, peace, juſtice, ſafety, and faithfulneſſe to your truſt may require you ſo to doe, becauſe it is the end, <hi>viz.</hi> Common ſafety, &amp; not the means, <hi>viz.</hi> Your Votes, Orders, Ordinances, &amp;c. muſt proſtrate and command you; yea, and as the caſe may ſtand, wee may be bound in conſcience to acquieſce therein: but when you have præpoſſeſſed our reaſons &amp; judgements not by bare Votes, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Ordinances, but by ſtrong and vigorous reaſons, debates &amp; arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch and ſuch things (not only affirmed, but argued to our full conviction) as <hi>bringing upon you the blood that hath been ſhed in theſe Wars,</hi> yea as <hi>plucking up the foundation of any hopes of ever ſetling a peace with the King, which ſhall be both juſt and ſure;</hi> yea tending to the <hi>apparent deſtruction of the Perſons which have engaged, and loſſe of the ends for which both Kingdomes have engaged in this Warre.</hi> Blame us not if we cannot reſt ſatisfied in your doing ſuch things, which in your owne judgments are ſo conducing; you may happily perſwade and argue downe your reaſons which have ſeized upon us, but you cannot order and vote them downe; we can proſtrate our opinion, but not our reaſon to your determination; Neither doe we take upon us to judge what is meet to be done for publique good, having choſen you to judge for us; but we rather reſt in your judgements enforc'd by arguments, then evidenced by meer votes, there we have your reaſon, here your will; we cannot preſume you would have us content our ſelves with your meere will and pleaſure, though to the apparent deſtruction of the wel affected of the Nation, contrary to all principles of reaſon and equity. You that have told us that a Kingdome muſt not be ruined at the meer will of the King, have taught us to inferre, that neither ſhould it be ſacrificed to the meer pleaſure of the Parliament, if it be not even <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus regis,</hi> much leffe then can it be <hi>volun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as Parliament,</hi> but <hi>ſalus populi;</hi> that is, <hi>ſuprema lex.</hi> Surely that God that did never appoint the lives, liberties and eſtates of millions to be at the meer will and pleaſure of the King, did never ordaine like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that theſe ſhould be at the meere will and pleaſure (contrary to expreſſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reaſon) of the Parliament: It is very poſſible that your Honours have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good reaſons, and that to ſatisfaction for what you doe, touching your reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a perſonall Treaty with the King before ſatisfaction and ſecurity given: if ſo, we humbly crave to ſee them, and we have done.</p>
               <p>But if not, we beſeech you conſider, <hi>How baſe &amp; DISHONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE a thing it would be for the Houſes of Parliament, being in that condition they are, to treat under the Gallowes, to treat as traytors, their cauſe being not juſtified, nor their Declarations againſt them as rebels recalled; and how FOOLISH a thing would it have been, being poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Sword according to their right, not to ſecure it from the Kings claim to the contrary to themſelves and poſterity, before they treated of any thing, to the end that neither they nor their poſterity might be put to play a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116771:6"/>nother bloody game for the ſame thing?</hi> Will you doe things ſentenced by your ſelves for <hi>baſe and diſhonorable?</hi> Have you wreſted the Sword from him and them that would have forced you to the <hi>Gallowes,</hi> and after all this will you be treated to the <hi>Gallowes?</hi> Have you not jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it a FOOLISH <hi>thing,</hi> that having poſſeſſion of the Sword, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your right, not to ſecure it to your ſelves and poſterity before you treat?</hi> Or muſt your ſelves and poſterity either reſolve for ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to let the Sword be alwayes held over your neckes, to keep you under, or elſe to <hi>play another bloody game for the ſame thing?</hi> You could not be cudgel'd into a treaty, and will you be caiol'd and chanted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a treaty before ſecurity and ſatisfaction given? We beſeech you inform us (for our judgements lye freely open'd to receive any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of reaſon from you) hath there not been <hi>ſo much innocent blood of his Majeſties good ſubjects ſhed in this war by his Commands and Commiſſions? Were not Iriſh Rebels brought over into both Kingdomes, as alſo Forces from forraigne parts?</hi> Was not <hi>the warre in Ireland fomented and prolonged by his Majeſty, whereby the three Kingdomes were brought neere to utter ruine and deſtruction?</hi> Were not theſe ſtrong reaſons here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore why <hi>you ſhould conceive, that untill his Maty had given ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſecurity</hi> there ſhould be no treaty? Have you not many times attempted to prevaile with the King by <hi>ſeverall advices and petitions, which were not onely without ſucceſſe, but that hath followed, which no ill counſell hath in former times produced, nor any age hath ſeen; namely, thoſe ſeverall Proclamations and Declarations againſt both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; whereby your actions have been declared treaſonable, and your perſons traytors? Did not the King ſet up his Standard againſt his Parliament; whereby he did put the two Houſes of Parliament, and in them the whole Kingdom out of his protection?</hi> Did he volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarily <hi>take down his Standard?</hi> Hath he <hi>recalled his ſaid Proclamations and Declarations,</hi> making you &amp; all that ſtuck to your traytors and rebels? If not, will you treate with him before he hath done it? we are not inſenſible of your preſent diſtractions through the great defection, and almoſt incredible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting of ſeverall parts of this kingdome, ſome ſhips at Sea, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of ſeverall in the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and many great zealots in the kingdomes cauſe, ſtriking hands with Malignants, in promoting their deſignes, motions, and petitions, to the apparent prejudice of the Parliaments cauſe, and the kingdomes intereſt, moſt ſtrangely and hypocritically pleading conſcience of Covenant, and yet breaking the expreſſe letter of the ſixth Article of the Covenant, wherein they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116771:6"/>have ſworn, <hi>not to ſuffer themſelves directly or indirectly, by whatſoever combination, perſwaſion, or terror, to be divided and with drawn from this bleſſed union and conjunction, whether to make defection to the contrary part, or to give themſelves to a deteſtable indifferencie or newtrality in this cauſe, which ſo much concerneth the glory of God, the good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and the honour of the King,</hi> but have ſworn that they ſhall <hi>all the dayes of their lives zealouſly and conſtantly continue therein againſt all oppoſitions, and promote the ſame according to their power, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We obſerve likewiſe the moſt baſe, abominable, and horrible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of ſome <hi>Scots,</hi> that have invaded this kingdome, to the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſtaine of their nation, and abhorring and hiſſing at them for a moſt deteſtable, diſhonorable, and diſſembling people by all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions round about them, to the perpetuall ſcandall of Religion, and the profeſſion thereof, and the ſottiſhneſſe, baſeneſſe, un-<hi>Engliſhneſſe</hi> of many of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, who moſt ſtupidly ſuffer a moſt falſe and treacherous, covetous and covenant-breaking people to bring their wives and children, and driue out the <hi>Engliſh</hi> out of their houſes and poſſeſſions, as if theſe (poore ſouls) came out of meere pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and love to help up reformation by an army of prophane wretches, commanded by known Cavaliers and Malignants, and to ſettle the King in a ſufficient poſture to deſtroy the Parliament, according to their Covenant, and by his authority to eſtabliſh Presbytery, which his ſoule abhorres according to the covenant, to maintain a firme peace between the two Nations by a bloody warre, according to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants and treaties, &amp;c. We are not, we <hi>ſay,</hi> unmindfull of theſe diſtractions thus befalling you, which we confeſſe may not onely put you to many ſtraits and difficulties, but provoke you to reſolve, that ſince the people will be deceived, they ſhould be deceived; and ſince they would be enſlaved, after God by the Parliament and their forces had freed them from it, they ſhould be enſlaved, &amp;c. But give us leave humbly to reply.</p>
               <p>Firſt of all, if the people for want of wiſdome and conſcience to themſelves and poſterity, ſhould reſolve to enſlave themſelves, ſince they cannot doe it but by your Concurrence; will your wiſedome and conſciences ſuffer you to conſent thereunto? Is it their ſinne ſo to doe, and your vertue to help it on by your reſolves? Are not you the Fathers of the Kingdome, and will you conſent to the childrens madneſſe: and becauſe they will deſtroy themſelves in a peltiſh fit, you will vote them a power to bring it about? Put the <hi>Militia</hi> into
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116771:7"/>their owne hands, that they may effect their owne deſtruction. Will they not deſtroy you as well as themſelves: and muſt they be enabled to doe all this by authority of Parliament? Doe you not ſee that men are mad, elſe would they doe as they doe? ſpread their garments and palm-branches, and cry <hi>hail</hi> to them that doe thirſt for their blood? and attempt with ſwords and ſtaves to apprehend and crucifie them, <hi>viz.</hi> the Parliament and Army, that under God have been their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours? And will you put the ſword into mad mens hands that would deſtroy all but their enemies; will not our neighbour-Nations that are lookers on, ſay we are all madde? Have not you beene fighting all this while for the <hi>Militia;</hi> and having gotten it by Victory, will you looſe it againe by Vote? Shall the <hi>Militia</hi> of the City or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be put into the hands of reall Malignants, though ſome of the ſecond Edition, who are the moſt dangerous, becauſe degenerate and deſperate? If a froward people will bring their owne blood, and the blood of the Kingdom: upon themſelves, let themſelves by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bring it about, and let not our Parliament joyne with them in that unnaturall act.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Had you not alwayes a party againſt you, yea as great, as ſtrong, as mal gnant as now appeares; though they are more da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, bold, and viſible; were you not in a worſe poſture many a time ſince theſe warres began, then even now you are in? Petitions appear out of <hi>Surrey, Kent, Eſſex, &amp;c.</hi> ſhewing their malignancy: but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all arts and tricks to get ſubſcriptions. Look upon their numbers, and ſee whether you have not as great a cauſe to judge a better, a more united and reſolved party for you, then againſt you?</p>
               <p>As for the Seas, is not God the God of the Seas, as well as of the Land? doth not he exerciſe his wonders for his people in the deepe as well as on the dry ground? doth not hee as well hold the waters in the hollow of his fiſt, as weigh the mountains in a ballance? Did not he as well lead <hi>Iſrael</hi> through the Sea, as through the Wilderneſſe? Hath he not road his circuit round the confines of the Kingdome for you: and can he not, or will he not, thinke you, ride upon the proud waves of the Sea for you, if you truſt in him? Is not the Sea his as well as the Land? Or can you thinke that our God is the God of the Land, and your enemies God the God of the Seas? And that as our God hath had his day by Land, ſo wil theirs have his day at Sea? Is not the Sea ſinfull as well as the Land: and may not God be now a purging the Sea, as wel as he hath been in purifying the Land? Can we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116771:7"/>thinke that he that hath puniſhed the tyranny of Kings and Nobles by Land, will now indulge the pyracie of Princes &amp; Traitors by Sea? It cannot enter into our hearts, that thoſe that have eſcaped the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous vengeance of God by Land, ſhall be now able to revenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on God by Sea? He that hath ſlain the Dragon by Land, hath power enough to deale with the <hi>Leviathan</hi> by Sea? <hi>If you believe, you ſhall ſee the glory of God</hi> by Sea as well as by Land. Be not diſcouraged; If you doe not decline and revolt from your juſt Cauſe, God will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt with your Revolters both by Sea and Land, and their revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhall be their repentance, and your perſeverance &amp; courage, your rejoycing.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, will you have no work for your faith to act upon? Hath not God driven backe your enemies hundreds by your tennes; hath he not often times divided the red Sea for you, broken the head of Dragons for you, cauſed mountains to be made plaines before you, thrown downe the walls of <hi>Jerico</hi> for you, redeemed you out of ſixe troubles, and out of ſeven? Hath hee not delivered you many a time out of your diſtreſſe? Looke back we beſeech you upon your ſeverall Orders and Ordinances for dayes of Thankſ-giving, and the cauſes thereof: and remember what <hi>Balaack</hi> often-times conſulted, and <hi>Balaam</hi> anſwered from Mount-<hi>Piſga</hi> to Mount-<hi>Peor</hi> from time to time. Shall your hands now hang downe, and your knees waxe fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and your hearts wither like graſſe, cauſing you to throw by that Cauſe with which God hath ſo frequently appeared for you. Review all Scripture ſtories, and other authentique writings, and compare all with theſe dayes of Gods appearances for you, and ſee if our eyes have not ſeene the Almighty renewing his works of old for you, and now will you faint? What, have all your Experiences, and all your Sermons begot no greater a faith, but that you ſhould be ready to faint and fall at your preſent troubles? Hath your faithfull God after all your experiences of his truth and goodneſſe ſo little credite with you?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vide Article 4. of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne league and covenant.</note>4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Doe your enemies multiply? who is the cauſe of it? Is it not your indulgence to them? Have not you ſaved many a thiefe from the Gallows, that is now ſtriving to cut your throats? Did you not vow and ſweare with hands lifted up to the moſt high God, that you would <hi>with all faithfulneſſe endeavour the diſcovery of Incəndiaries, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, and evill Inſtruments,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that they may be brought to publique tryall, and receive CONDIGNE puniſhment.</hi> And have you done thus?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116771:8"/>what means then the beating of poor ſheep in many Counties againſt the oppreſſing Malignants, admitted for Deputi-Lieutenants: yea into ſeverall Committees, where they have vexed your friends for their faithfulneſſe to you. Are not theſe the men that <hi>prove goades in your ſides, and thorns in your eyes?</hi> Doth not God ſeem to reſolve to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject you from retaining your wonted authority in the Kingdome, as he did <hi>Saul</hi> from being King: And is it not for the ſame cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> your ſparing of <hi>Agags,</hi> whom you ſhould have hewen in pieces by the ſword of Juſtice for that blood which they have ſhed, making many women childleſſe in this Kingdome? Shall the feare of the people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you as it did him from doing Juſtice? Is not God to be feared more then the people? Doth not the cry of blood, <hi>Iriſh-blood, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh-blood,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh-blood</hi> make a noiſe in your eares? Will not God make inquiſition for blood? Was there ever ſo much blood ſpilt, and ſo little inquiſition made for blood as there hath beene ſince this <hi>Parliament</hi> began? And have you not juſt cauſe to feare, leſt your lives ſhould goe for theirs? Conſidering what Promiſes &amp; Covenants you have made, to bring ſuch bloody Delinquents unto condigne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: and what opportunities have you had to perform the ſame. Shall not <hi>Agag,</hi> and the fatteſt Malignants be only ſpared againſt all lawes of juſtice and equity: but muſt theſe have ſwords put into their hands again? <hi>Will they not hew you in pieces before the Lord,</hi> for ſparing them contrary to Gods command, and the expreſſe letter of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant? We beſeech you conſider, were there ever ſuch horrible things committed: ſo many Riots, Rebellions, Treaſons, Murthers, and blood-ſhed, perpetrated in this Kingdome and ſo little juſtice done upon ſuch Delinquents, as there have beene ſince you have had the government of the Kingdome in your hands? 'Tis true indeed, <hi>before</hi> this Parliament, thoſe were ſmitten, which ſhould have been ſpared: and <hi>ſince</hi> this Parliament, have not many been ſpared, which ſhould have beene ſmitten? <hi>Then</hi> the righteous were condemned, and <hi>now</hi> are not the wicked juſtified? And is not the one as well as the other an abhomination unto the Lord? Did not puniſhing the innocent by our former Rulers make them &amp; their government deſpiſed of God? And doth not ſparing the guilty by our preſent Rulers, make them and their government ſcorned of men, and diſpleaſing to God? And can theſe be long liv'd that are rejected both by God and men? Looke upon your Petitioners, eſpecially the capitall among them of <hi>Kent, Eſſex, Surrey,</hi> and ſend for an informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116771:8"/>of thoſe grave and wel-affected Citizens, that you hear of, ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſoliciting the Common-councel of <hi>London</hi> to Petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you for a Perſonall Treaty at <hi>London:</hi> and enquire who in the ſaid Common-Councell are ſuch ſticklers for the ſaid Petitions, and you will eaſily find who they are that trouble you: and whether your indulgence to Malignants, and thoſe that are yours, and your Armies enemies are not the great cauſe of your preſent troubles both from <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in our owne Kingdome. Were thoſe caſt out of the Common-Councell upon whom the plaine characters of malignancy are ſtampt, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Thoſe that did not contribute voluntarily for the ſervice of the Parliament, according to their Propoſitions. 2. Thoſe that have been diſarmed. 3. Thoſe that have been impriſoned for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy. 4. Thoſe that have had a hand in the Treaſonable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement. 5. Thoſe that have beene, and are moſt notorious ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to your Forces, contrary to their ſolemn Vow and Covenant. 6. Thoſe that did abett the horrible force upon the two Houſes, &amp;c. You ſhould quickely ſee another face, both upon the Common-Councell, and whole Citie, then now you doe: Neither ſhould ſuch lying Pamphlets, ſcurrillous Ballads, ſcandalous Libels, and ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Papers, made on purpoſe to caſt dirt into the face of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be ſuffered to be ſold in the moſt publique places, even at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and elſe-where as now they are; never was there ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt caſt upon Authority as is now, even in the great Citie it ſelfe: And no marvell, ſince the quondam awfull authority of Parliament it ſelfe is ſo ſcorned and abuſed, and no juſtice done upon offenders in this kind, inſomuch that it is almoſt dangerous for a man to plead for the Parliaments authority, and for a Parliament ſouldier that fights for their Cauſe, to ride through the City: and who can won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at it, when no man ſuffered for that horrible force made upon the Houſes to the amazement of all beholders. Nay, it is to be wiſht that there were not of thoſe reverend gown-men that encouraged thoſe villains in that Rebellion, ſitting in Common-councell, and contriving their ruine. If you will ſuffer your authority thus to lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, the peace and welfare of the whole Kingdome will alſo languiſh and periſh.</p>
               <p>Are not Murders, Felonies, Treaſons, Burglaries, Mutinies, Inſurrections, committed even in the great Citie, ſo that blood lies upon it, and diſquiets it (though we minde not the cauſe of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent troubles) &amp; no juſtice at al done: A noyſe we hear of a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116771:9"/>of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> for the trials of thoſe horrible things, as alſo of votes making ſuch as riſe up fomenting a new warre in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Counties, guilty of high treaſon, that thoſe that invited the <hi>Scots</hi> into this Kingdome, are traytors, &amp;c. But though you have ſeverall in your hands, yet the worſt that comes to them is, that they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured in priſon (it may be but for ſome few dayes neither) from the hands of the Souldiers that would give them their due if they could meet them in the field; ſo that your Votes, and Orders, and Ordinances, and Declarations threatning ſuch and ſuch things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Delinquents, what are they but <hi>Fulmina bruta,</hi> the crackling of gun-pots, and no more regarded; paltry Pamphlets, prophane Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lads, to the diſhonour of God, ſcorn and ſcandall of the Parliament, ſold and ſung in open ſtreets. Is not the Parliament made the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards ſong, toſt up and down in the lewd lips of idle tiplers, in every Taphouſe and Tavern? whereas in ſeverall Countries you ſhall ſcarce heare a man to open his mouth againſt the Parliament, the reaſon is, becauſe they are preſently ſnapt up by order of ſome diligent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee or other. Were the ſame courſe taken in the Citie, would not the ſame effect follow thereon? Neither can it be ſaid that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not execute iuſtice, the people are ſo tumultuous, &amp;c. for the longer you ſuſpend it the more unable you will be for it, and if you doe well, who will harm you? Is not juſtice Gods ordinance, and will he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline his own ordinance? Did he ever deny his aſſiſting you in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of juſtice (at leaſt if you did exerciſe that authority and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in doing it as you might? Was not the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> the dread of Princes, and is it not now the ſcorn of Peſants? Did not the execution of juſtice even upon Princes, make them the dread of the one, and the neglect of juſtice even upon peaſants (rogues and vagrants abuſing you in open ſtreets) make you the ſcorn of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Nay, would you even now blind your eyes to all carnall fears, &amp; diſcouragements, and feare not the face of man, profeſſe and practice, we ſay again, PRACTISE principles of juſtice and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the Kingdome, God would ſubdue the people under you, and your friends would multiply and love you, your enemies would moulder away, and feare and tremble before you, and you would yet cauſe the peace and welfare of this kingdom (which is now withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring under your hands) to flouriſh and proſper, and both our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent times, and ages to come, would call you <hi>Bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116771:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
